Guide to the Walter L. Pforzheimer Collection of Century Company Illustrations
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
[Walter L. Pforzheimer collection of Century Company illustrations].
1879-1914
GEN MSS 1219
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.1
(17 boxes)
The collection consists of 142 drawings and watercolors by twenty-seven artists who were commissioned by the Century Company to create illustrations for their popular periodicals The Century Illustrated Monthly Magazine and St. Nicholas Magazine, in particular to illustrate stories for children. Most of the drawings have paper labels or production marks in crayon on their versos indicating the magazine, volume number, and projected page number where the images were to appear, the section of the magazine (such as "Open Letters" to the editor or the "In Lighter Vein" departments), prices paid to the artists, and notes such as "Plate wanted," "Blueprint at once," and "Great Haste!" While many prominent illustrators from the era are included in the collection, those represented by the largest number of drawings are Reginald B. Birch (10), Harrison Cady (9), Oliver Herford (22), Charles M. Relyea (47), and I. W. Taber (8).
Pforzheimer, Walter L. (Walter Lionel), 1914-2003
Benda, Wladyslaw T. (Wladyslaw Theodore), 1873-1948
Birch, Reginald B., 1856-1943
Blaisdell, E. Warde
Blum, Robert Frederick, 1857-1903
Blumenschein, E. L. (Ernest Leonard), 1874-1960
Bransom, Paul, 1885-1979
Brennan, Alfred, 1853-1921
Cady, Harrison, 1877-1970
Church, Frederick S. (Frederick Stuart), 1842-1924
Cox, Kenyon, 1856-1919
Edwards, George Wharton, 1859-1950
Gaul, Gilbert William, 1855-1919
Harker, G. A.
Herford, Oliver, 1863-1935
Kemble, E. W. (Edward Windsor), 1861-1933
Lungren, Fernand, 1857-1932
Lutz, Edwin George, 1868-
Nuttall, Charles
Post, Charles Johnson, 1873-1956
Potthast, Edward, 1857-1927
Price, Norman, 1877-1951
Raleigh, Henry, 1880-1945
Relyea, C. M. (Charles M.), 1863-1932
Storer, Florence Edith
Taber, I. W. (Isaac Walton), 1857-1933
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Walter L. Pforzheimer (Yale 1935, 1938L), 1955.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Walter L. Pforzheimer (1914-2003)
Walter L. Pforzheimer (Yale 1935, 1938L), lawyer, intelligence officer, and book collector.
Century Company (1881-1933)
The Century Company was an American publisher of books and magazines. Founded in 1870 in New York City as Scribner and Company, a subsidiary of Charles Scribner's Sons, it was purchased in 1881 by Roswell Smith and renamed the Century Company. The firm's magazine, Scribner's Monthly, also founded in 1870, was renamed The Century Illustrated Monthly Magazine in 1881; it ceased publication in 1930. The Century Company also became the publisher of the children's periodical St. Nicholas Magazine, which had been founded by Scribner and Company in 1873; it ceased publication in 1940. In 1933 the Century Company merged with publisher D. Appleton & Company to form the Appleton-Century Company, Appleton-Century-Crofts.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of 142 drawings and watercolors by twenty-seven artists who were commissioned by the Century Company to create illustrations for their popular periodicals The Century Illustrated Monthly Magazine and St. Nicholas Magazine, in particular to illustrate stories for children. Most of the drawings have paper labels or production marks in crayon on their versos indicating the magazine, volume number, and projected page number where the images were to appear, the section of the magazine (such as "Open Letters" to the editor or the "In Lighter Vein" departments), prices paid to the artists, and notes such as "Plate wanted," "Blueprint at once," and "Great Haste!" While many prominent illustrators from the era are included in the collection, those represented by the largest number of drawings are Reginald B. Birch (10), Harrison Cady (9), Oliver Herford (22), Charles M. Relyea (47), and I. W. Taber (8).
Arrangement
Arranged alphabetically by artist, and by size thereunder.
Century illustrated monthly magazine; St. Nicholas (New York, N.Y.); Children's literature -- Illustrations; Children's periodicals, American; Periodical illustrations -- United States -- 19th century; Periodical illustrations -- United States -- 20th Century; Watercolors (paintings) -- United States -- 19th century; Watercolors (paintings) -- United States -- 20th Century; Illustrators -- United States -- 19th century; Illustrators -- United States -- 20th Century; Benda, Wladyslaw T. (Wladyslaw Theodore), 1873-1948; Birch, Reginald B., 1856-1943; Blaisdell, E. Warde; Blum, Robert Frederick, 1857-1903; Blumenschein, E. L. (Ernest Leonard), 1874-1960; Bransom, Paul, 1885-1979; Brennan, Alfred, 1853-1921; Cady, Harrison, 1877-1970; Church, Frederick S. (Frederick Stuart), 1842-1924; Cox, Kenyon, 1856-1919; Edwards, George Wharton, 1859-1950; Gaul, Gilbert William, 1855-1919; Harker, G. A.; Herford, Oliver, 1863-1935; Kemble, E. W. (Edward Windsor), 1861-1933; Lungren, Fernand, 1857-1932; Lutz, Edwin George, 1868-; Nuttall, Charles; Pforzheimer, Walter L. (Walter Lionel), 1914-2003; Post, Charles Johnson, 1873-1956; Potthast, Edward, 1857-1927; Price, Norman, 1877-1951; Raleigh, Henry, 1880-1945; Relyea, C. M. (Charles M.), 1863-1932; Storer, Florence Edith; Taber, I. W. (Isaac Walton), 1857-1933; Century Company
- Drawings, 1879-1914; 2.1; (17 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by artist, and by size thereunder.
  Scope and Contents
  Short titles were used in place of The Century Illustrated Monthly Magazine and St. Nicholas Magazine.
  - Benda, Wladyslaw T. (Wladyslaw Theodore)
    - "Spinning" for St. Nicholas; graphite and wash on illustration board, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Birch, Reginald B.
    - "The Cochonette" for Century; ink on illustration board, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - "Linsy-woolsy" for St. Nicholas; ink on paper mounted on pulpboard, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - "He croons a little song (hugging the rabbit)" for St. Nicholas; ink on Bristol board, 1894 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - "Once lived a lass" for Century; ink on Bristol board, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Tailpiece in "Jacquelin of Holland" for Century; ink on Bristol board, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Tailpiece: "A Valentine" for St. Nicholas; ink on Bristol board, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Tailpiece: valentine for Century; ink on illustration board, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - "Bachelor of means" for St. Nicholas; ink on Bristol board, undated (Box 7, Folder 64)
    - "Building the ship" for St. Nicholas; ink on Bristol board, undated (Box 7, Folder 65)
    - "Betty finds her mother" for unidentified publication; ink on Bristol board mounted on illustration board, undated (Box 14, Folder 117)
  - Blaisdell, E. Warde
    - "Early Morning Plunge" for St. Nicholas; ink and watercolor on illustration board, 1903 (Box 12, Folder 104)
    - "Doctor and Patient" for Century; ink and watercolor on illustration board, undated (Box 12, Folder 105)
    - "Obliging" for Century; ink and watercolor on illustration board, undated (Box 12, Folder 106)
    - "The Old Old Story" for Century; ink and watercolor on illustration board, undated (Box 12, Folder 107)
  - Blum, Robert Frederick
    - "Japanese Strawcoat" for St. Nicholas; ink on illustration board, undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Blumenschein, E. L. (Ernest Leonard)
    - Untitled [fishermen pulling nets] for Century; graphite, ink, and charcoal on illustration board, undated (Box 14, Folder 118)
  - Bransom, Paul
    - "Monkey" for Century; crayon and watercolor on paper mounted on laminated board, 1909 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - "Performing Seals" for Century; crayon and watercolor on paper mounted on illustration board, undated (Box 14, Folder 119)
  - Brennan, Alfred
    - "The procession through the wood" for St. Nicholas; watercolor on paper, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - "The Bamboo" by Mary McNeil Scott, for Century; ink on paper, undated (Box 7, Folder 66)
  - Cady, Harrison
    - "The deaf old gentleman" for St. Nicholas; watercolor on illustration board, undated (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Happy Chaps: "A caterpillar sold sarsaparilla" for St. Nicholas; ink on Bristol board, undated (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - "Happy Chaps dancing" for St. Nicholas; ink on Bristol board, 1908 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - "Happy Chaps: planning for Jollipopolis" for St. Nicholas; ink on Bristol board, undated (Box 3, Folder 27-29)
    - "On the appletree bough" for St. Nicholas; watercolor on illustration board, undated (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - "When Uncle Jerry Centipede goes fishing" for St. Nicholas; ink and wash on illustration board, undated (Box 12, Folder 108)
    - "Happy Chaps Field Day" for St. Nicholas; ink and sepia wash on illustration board, 1908 (Box 14, Folder 120)
  - Church, Frederick S. (Frederick Stuart)
    - "That's good -- give me another" for St. Nicholas; graphite on paper, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Cox, Kenyon
    - Initial M for "The Clock Mender" for Century; ink on paper, 1887 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Illustrations of the Trappist monks at the Abbey of Gethsemani for Century; ink on paper, 1887 (Box 7, Folder 67-68)
    - "Malay Village" for Century; watercolor on illustration board, 1891 (Box 7, Folder 69)
    - "Mère Angelique" for Century; ink on paper, 1890 (Box 7, Folder 70)
  - Edwards, George Wharton
    - "Entertaining baby" for St. Nicholas; ink on Bristol board, undated (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - "The Great de Keyser" for Century; ink on Bristol board, 1889 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - "A daughter of the Tow" for Century; crayon on paper mounted on illustration board, undated (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - "Jillis," in "Violoncello of Jugfrow Rosenboom" for Century; ink on illustration board, undated (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - "Tea at the Temple" for Century; ink on Bristol board, undated (Box 7, Folder 71)
    - "Peasants of Batz and Guimilliere" for Century; watercolor on illustration board, 1896 (Box 12, Folder 109)
  - Gaul, William Gilbert
    - "A Jamaica Street" for Century; oil on canvas mounted on illustration board, 1893 (Box 13, Folder 110)
  - Harker, G. A.
    - "Under April Skies" for St. Nicholas; ink and wash on illustration board, undated (Box 4, Folder 36)
    - "Before the Fire" for St. Nicholas; watercolor on illustration board, undated (Box 7, Folder 72)
    - "The Hare Family" for St. Nicholas; watercolor on illustration board, undated (Box 7, Folder 73)
    - "Into the Brook" for St. Nicholas; watercolor on illustration board, undated (Box 7, Folder 74)
    - "The Two Engines" for St. Nicholas; ink and wash on illustration board, undated (Box 7, Folder 75)
    - "What's the matter, Mr. Squirrel?" for St. Nicholas; watercolor on illustration board, undated (Box 13, Folder 111)
    - "The Snow," for St. Nicholas; crayon on illustration board, undated (Box 14, Folder 121)
  - Herford, Oliver
    - "Checkmating New Year's Resolutions" for Century; ink and collage on Bristol board, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - "Collapse of the International Club" for Century; ink on Bristol board mounted on pulpboard, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "Country life in America" for Century; ink on Bristol board mounted on pulpboard, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - "It's all right Jack, we missed the chicken after all" for Century; ink on Bristol board mounted on pulpboard, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - "On agitation versus repose for women" for Century; ink on Bristol board mounted on pulpboard, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - "On allowing the editor to shop early for Christmas" for Century; ink on Bristol board mounted on pulpboard, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - "On the two kinds of reporters" for Century; ink on Bristol board mounted on pulpboard, untitled (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - "Set back to English Socialism" for Century; ink on Bristol board mounted on pulpboard, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - "The sculptor fell in love with it: a Cubist romance" for Century; ink on Bristol board mounted on pulpboard, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Untitled (bird on a branch) for Century; ink on Bristol board mounted on pulpboard, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Untitled (lyre) for Century; ink on Bristol board mounted on pulpboard, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - "Boastful butterfly" for Century; ink and colored pencil on Bristol board, 1898 (Box 4, Folder 37-38)
    - "A cold day" for St. Nicholas; ink on Bristol board, undated (Box 4, Folder 39)
    - "The critics" for St. Nicholas; ink on Bristol board, undated (Box 4, Folder 40)
    - "Dwarf and giants at dinner" for St. Nicholas; ink and watercolor on Bristol board, undated (Box 4, Folder 41)
    - "Highest enjoyment of music" for Century; ink on paper mounted on pulpboard, undated (Box 4, Folder 42)
    - No. 3 in "The Hours" for Century; ink on paper mounted on pulpboard, undated (Box 4, Folder 43)
    - No. 5 in "The Hours" for Century; ink on paper mounted on pulpboard, undated (Box 4, Folder 44)
    - "On the high cost of living" for Century; ink on paper mounted on board, undated (Box 4, Folder 45)
    - "Poseur" for Century; ink on paper mounted on board, undated (Box 4, Folder 46)
    - "A young student" for St. Nicholas; ink on paper, undated (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - Kemble, E. W. (Edward Windsor)
    - Five baseball sketches for St. Nicholas; ink on paper mounted on illustration board, 1891 (Box 5, Folder 48)
  - Lungren, Fernand
    - "Day dreams (the pier)" for St. Nicholas; watercolor on illustration board, undated (Box 5, Folder 49)
    - "Fagged out" for St. Nicholas; watercolor on paper, 1879 (Box 5, Folder 50)
    - "In the village store" for St. Nicholas; ink and watercolor on Bristol board, undated (Box 5, Folder 51)
    - "Christmas Eve" for St. Nicholas; watercolor on paper mounted on illustration board, 1894 (Box 13, Folder 112)
    - "The Tennis Court" for St. Nicholas; watercolor on paper mounted on illustration board, 1908 (Box 15, Folder 122)
    - Untitled [train station waiting room] for Century; watercolor on illustration board, undated (Box 15, Folder 123)
  - Lutz, Edwin George
    - "Rabbit prestidigitator" for St. Nicholas; ink on Bristol board, 1909 (Box 8, Folder 76)
  - Nuttall, Charles
    - "Daily Reminder" for Century; ink on illustration board, 1907 (Box 8, Folder 77)
    - "Gittin' reckless" for Century; ink on illustration board, 1907 (Box 8, Folder 78)
  - Post, Charles Johnson
    - "Caramba!" for Century; ink on paper, undated (Box 5, Folder 52)
  - Potthast, Edward
    - "Behind the scenes" [New York Aquarium] for Century; watercolor on illustration board, 1900 (Box 8, Folder 79)
  - Price, Norman
    - "A French Kitchen" for Century; watercolor and oil on illustration board, undated (Box 8, Folder 80)
  - Raleigh, Henry
    - Initial U for Century; ink on paper, undated (Box 5, Folder 53)
  - Relyea, C. M. (Charles M.)
    - For "Abbie Ann"
      - "Knocking at the door" for St. Nicholas; watercolor on illustration board, undated (Box 9, Folder 83)
      - "School girls" for St. Nicholas; watercolor on illustration board, undated (Box 13, Folder 113)
      - "At the milliners" for St. Nicholas; watercolor and graphite on illustration board, undated (Box 15, Folder 124)
      - "In the park" for St. Nicholas; watercolor and graphite on illustration board, undated (Box 15, Folder 125)
      - "The new hat" for St. Nicholas; watercolor and graphite on illustration board, undated (Box 15, Folder 126)
    - For " Pretty Polly Perkins"
      - "Polly and her father" for St. Nicholas; watercolor on illustration board, undated (Box 5, Folder 54)
      - "Polly and her mother (Homeward Bound)" for St. Nicholas; watercolor on illustration board, undated (Box 10, Folder 97)
      - "The pony cart" for St. Nicholas; watercolor on illustration board, undated (Box 11, Folder 98)
      - "A Curious Chariot" for St. Nicholas; oil on illustration board, undated (Box 13, Folder 115)
      - "Bringing the supper" for St. Nicholas; crayon on illustration board, undated (Box 16, Folder 134)
    - "Riding a jumper" for St. Nicholas; watercolor and ink on paper mounted on illustration board, undated (Box 5, Folder 55)
    - "The Trough" for St. Nicholas; watercolor on illustration board, undated (Box 5, Folder 56)
    - "Amateur theatricals" for St. Nicholas; watercolor on illustration board, undated (Box 9, Folder 84)
    - "At the spinet" for St. Nicholas; watercolor on illustration board, undated (Box 9, Folder 85)
    - "The Bicycle Race" for St. Nicholas; watercolor on illustration board, undated (Box 9, Folder 86)
    - "The Class Rush" for St. Nicholas; ink on paper, 1904 (Box 9, Folder 87)
    - "Confidences" for St. Nicholas; watercolor on Bristol board, undated (Box 9, Folder 88)
    - "The Dance" for St. Nicholas; watercolor on illustration board, undated (Box 9, Folder 89)
    - "Dosia's Day" by Margaret Johnson for St. Nicholas; watercolor, ink, and gouache on illustration board, undated (Box 9, Folder 90)
    - "Getting in the way" for St. Nicholas; watercolor on illustration board, 1896 (Box 10, Folder 91)
    - "In the Indian canoe" for St. Nicholas; watercolor on illustration board, undated (Box 10, Folder 92)
    - "In Norse Land" for St. Nicholas; watercolor on paper (accompanied by illustration board), 1897 (Box 10, Folder 93)
    - "The New Hat" for St. Nicholas; watercolor on paper mounted on illustration board, 1899 (Box 10, Folder 94)
    - "A Norse Lullaby" for St. Nicholas; graphite and watercolor on illustration board, 1896 (Box 10, Folder 95)
    - "Playing School" for St. Nicholas; watercolor on illustration board, undated (Box 10, Folder 96)
    - "Pony Sled" for St. Nicholas; watercolor on illustration board, undated (Box 11, Folder 99)
    - "The Sewing Club" for St. Nicholas; watercolor on illustration board, undated (Box 11, Folder 100)
    - "Sweet Study" for St. Nicholas; watercolor on illustration board, undated (Box 11, Folder 101)
    - Untitled [birdcage, vignette for tailpiece] for St. Nicholas; watercolor on illustration board, undated (Box 11, Folder 102)
    - Untitled [crow on a stump]; for St. Nicholas; watercolor on illustration board, undated (Box 11, Folder 103)
    - "In Venice" for St. Nicholas; watercolor on illustration board, undated (Box 13, Folder 114)
    - "A warning to mother" for St. Nicholas; watercolor on illustration board, undated (Box 13, Folder 116)
    - "At the Shore" and "By the Brook" for St. Nicholas; watercolor on illustration board, undated (Box 15, Folder 127)
      General
      For "Nature and Science for Young Folks," edited by Edward F. Bigelow
    - "A Capsize" for St. Nicholas; watercolor on illustration board, undated (Box 15, Folder 128)
    - "Coming from school" for St. Nicholas; watercolor on illustration board, undated (Box 15, Folder 129)
    - "Flight of the Geese" for St. Nicholas; watercolor on illustration board, 1895 (Box 16, Folder 130)
    - "The Houseboat" for St. Nicholas; oil on illustration board, undated (Box 16, Folder 131)
    - "In a College Room" for St. Nicholas; watercolor graphite on illustration board, 1904 (Box 16, Folder 132)
    - "The introduction" for St. Nicholas; watercolor, graphite, and crayon on illustration board, 1907 (Box 16, Folder 133)
    - "Reading the news" for St. Nicholas; crayon and watercolor on illustration board, 1900 (Box 16, Folder 135)
    - Illustration for "Surfman No. 7" for St. Nicholas; graphite, crayon, and watercolor on illustration board, undated (Box 17, Folder 136)
    - "The solo" for St. Nicholas; watercolor on illustration board, undated (Box 17, Folder 137)
    - "Teammates" for St. Nicholas; watercolor on illustration board, undated (Box 17, Folder 138)
    - "Trouble in the nursery" for St. Nicholas; watercolor and graphite on illustration board, undated (Box 17, Folder 139)
    - "Under the birches" for St. Nicholas; watercolor on illustration board, undated (Box 17, Folder 140)
    - Illustration for "When Woods are Green" for Century; watercolor on illustration board, undated (Box 17, Folder 141)
    - Untitled [children and governesses in park] for St. Nicholas; ink and wash on illustration board, undated (Box 17, Folder 142)
  - Storer, Florence Edith
    - "Rabbits in the Wood" for St. Nicholas; ink and watercolor on illustration board, undated (Box 8, Folder 81)
  - Taber, I. W. (Isaac Walton)
    - "Grasshopper Bicycle Race" for St. Nicholas; watercolor on illustration board, 1896 (Box 6, Folder 57-58)
    - "The Grasshopper Ball" for St. Nicholas; watercolor on illustration board, 1896 (Box 6, Folder 59-61)
    - "Grasshopper Baseball" for St. Nicholas; watercolor on illustration board, 1896 (Box 6, Folder 62-63)
    - "Chinese Wildcat" for St. Nicholas; ink on illustration board, 1895 (Box 8, Folder 82)